「良医」前情回顾
Previously on "The Good Doctor"...
表现得像个普通人能有多难
How hard can it be to just act like a normal human being?
不
No!
你能别玩你那破兔子了吗
Will you stop petting that stupid rabbit?!
我们再也不会回家了
We're never going home again.
我们有彼此  这就够了
We have each other, and that's all we need.
你未婚夫的刀法不错
Your fiancé sure can handle a knife.
他有严重的缺陷
He's got a serious deficit.
你是骄傲还是失望
So, are you proud or disappointed?
马库斯  别掺杂个人情绪
Marcus, stop making everything so personal.
你从上班第一天起就想要他的职位
You've wanted his job since day one.
在座各位都知道
Everyone in this room knows that.
-你怎么  -这是我的科室
- How did you... - It's my department.
我需要了解一切
It's my job to know everything.
那既然我为你工作
Since I work for you,
这是不是都算你的错
doesn't that make all this actually your fault?
不好意思  我只听到「我为你工作」
Oh, I'm sorry. I stopped listening after "I work for you".
一个外科医生需要懂得沟通
A surgeon needs to communicate.
莫菲医生能吗  重压之下他能行吗
Can Dr. Murphy do that? Can he do that under stress?
明知别人真的命悬一线时
Can he do that knowing that a human life
他能做到吗
literally hangs in the balance?
我正在玩「神秘海域」  没电了
So, I'm in the middle of "Uncharted", and I'm dead.
能借我几粒7号电池吗
Can I borrow some triple A's?
我是你的邻居
I'm your neighbor.
你好
Hello.
住34号
34?
我上周搬来的  住33号
I moved in last week. 33.
我知道
Yeah, I know.
我在医院上班
I work at a hospital.
太酷了
That's cool.
是啊
Yes.
7号电池  拜托啦
Triple A's, por favor?
电池
Batteries.
对
Right.
你有吗
Do you have any?
7号电池
Triple A batteries.
谢谢
Thank you.
给你个建议  别喂猫
Piece of advice -- don't feed the cat.
哪只猫
Which cat?
你喂它一次  它就赖着不走了
Feed it once, and it'll never leave you alone.
谢谢你的电池  邻居
Thank you for the batteries, neighbor.
不客气
You're welcome!
外科
Surgical.
算你运气好  我不是护士
Well, you're in luck because I'm not a nurse,
我是外科住院医师
I'm a surgical resident.
有什么事吗
How can I help you?
找到跟查克匹配的肝源了
We got a liver for Chuck!
-在哪  -旧金山市医院
- Where? - SF Municipal Hospital!
肝脏从摘除到移植能存活多久
And how long do we have body-to-body on the liver transplant?
-八小时  -八小时
- Eight hours. - Eight hours.
你不知道肝脏的存活时间
You don't know the longevity of a liver?
这里是教学医院  我是老师
This is a teaching hospital, and I'm the teacher.
你和莫菲负责去取器官
You and Murphy, you're on organ pick-up.
检查健康情况  把肝脏从旧市医带回来
Check the health and bring the liver back from SFM.
是我接收的查克  我真的很想
I was at Chuck's intake. I'd really like to be --
那你现在负责接收他的新肝脏
Now you're gonna be at the intake for his new liver.
杰瑞德  带查克下来准备好
Jared, get Chuck down here and get him prepped.
肝脏只能存活八小时
We got eight hours on this thing,
时间不等人
and the clock starts ticking now.
本德尔医生请到精神科病房
Dr. Bender to the mental ward, please.
本德尔医生
Dr. Bender.
我没有打扰你的术前准备吧
I'm not interrupting your pre-game, am I?
这是我第四百台乳房重建手术
I think this is my 400th breast reconstruction.
董事会真该送我块牌匾
The board should give me a plaque.
怎么了
What's up?
下午四点
Your 4:00 P.M.
VIP患者万纳梅克
The V.I.P. -- Wannamaker.
对  皮瓣移植
Yes! The Free-Flap.
他住进了顶层豪华套房
He's checked into the penthouse suite,
肯定住得很舒适
resting comfortably I'm sure.
我给他做了一段时间工作  他就快答应
I've been working on him for awhile now, and he's close.
给基金会减免税款了
He's real close to making the Foundation his tax relief.
太好了
That's good to hear.
我要手术万无一失
I want aces on this.
一切都要完美
Everything perfect.
你这么想就好  我正打算通知呢
That's good to know. I was gonna phone it in.
本德尔医生请到精神科病房
Dr. Bender to the mental ward, please.
本德尔医生
Dr. Bender.
这是主席式的动员谈话吗
Is this the chairman's version of a pep talk?
我是给手术上个保险
I'm looking for a fail-safe outcome on the procedure.
我想让梅伦德斯医生做你的助手
I want you to use Dr. Melendez as your second.
他就是你的「保险」  梅伦德斯
That's your fail-safe? Melendez?
我才是你的外科主任
I'm your Chief of Surgery.
这只是保障完美手术的预防措施
It's just a precaution to guarantee a perfect outcome.
你在质疑我的能力吗
Are you doubting my abilities?
万纳梅克很重要
Wannamaker is important.
一切必须做到完美
Everything has to be perfect.
你已经说过了
You said that already.
我才是你的「保险」
I'm your fail-safe.
那个VIP患者不会有事的
The V.I.P. will be fine.
你没事吧
How you doing?
我知道你可能受不了这些动静
I know these sounds and everything might be a lot for you.
谁都难以承受
It's -- it's hard for anyone.
我喜欢直升机
I like helicopters.
我不知道你坐过直升机
I, uh, didn't know you'd been on a helicopter.
我没坐过
I haven't.
十五分钟后到达旧金山市立医院
15 minutes to San Francisco Municipal Hospital.
飞行应该很平稳
Should be a smooth ride.
你知道这算什么吧
You do know what this is, right?
我告诉你吧  这就是打杂
Well, I'll tell you what it is. It's scut work.
杰拉德有黄金入场券  而我们只能...
Jared gets the golden ticket, and we get...
送披萨外卖
pizza delivery.
螺旋桨会一圈圈转下去  肖恩
The rotors just go round and round, Shaun.
不会变的
They don't change.
怎样才能跟你聊天呢
How do I talk to you?
查克  你觉得胸痛气短吗
So, Chuck, any chest pains, shortness of breath?
没有
No.
最近六个月内喝过酒吗
Any alcohol in the last six months?
没有
No.
-会疼一下  -四肢有水肿吗
-Here comes a quick pinch. -Any swelling in your limbs?
这里跟黑色星期五的沃尔玛一样
It's Walmart on Black Friday in here.
准备器官移植时就会这样紧张
Things speed way up - when you're having a transplant.
我喜欢
I like it.
这是正能量
It's good energy.
所以没有水肿是吧
So, that's a "No" on the swelling?
没有
No.
我时常情绪低落
I feel lousy all the time, pretty much.
但...有了这个肝我就有了第二次生命
But...I've got a second chance, you know, with this liver.
当然
Sure.
抱歉  我女儿的电话
Excuse me. It's my daughter.
我跟妈妈说过了
I already spoke to Mom.
还有汤米叔叔
A-And Uncle Tommy, too.
是啊  我得亲眼看到你
Yeah, I need to see your face.
好的
All right.
我爱你
I love you.
再见
Bye.
她刚从加州大学法学院毕业
She just graduated from law school at Cal.
我跟你说过
I told you that.
没说过  恭喜了
Uh, no. Congratulations.
那我应该是跟布朗医生说过
I must've told Dr. Browne, then.
布朗医生呢
Where is Dr. Browne?
肝源在这里
Here's your liver.
需要你签个字
I'm going to need you to sign for it.
标准操作流程是
Standard operating procedure is to leave the liver
把肝留在供体腹腔内
in the safety of the body cavity.
我知道流程
I'm aware of the procedure.
本来移植名单上有个无名氏排在前面
We had a John Doe - at the top of the registry,
但还没来得及移植那人就死了
but that John Doe died before we could plant.
你们摘取多久了
How long ago did you take it out?
三小时
Three hours.
我们一下少了三小时
We just lost three hours.
准确得说是三小时五分钟
Technically three hours and five minutes.
冷藏箱上有准确时间
True clock is on the cooler.
不得低于四摄氏度或高于八摄氏度
Can't go below 39 degrees or above 47 degrees.
可以签字了吗
You want to sign for it?
组织看起来很健康
Tissue looks healthy.
你在干什么
What are you doing?
你在找什么
What are you looking for?
-他干嘛呢  -我不知道
-What's he doing? - I'm not sure.
肖恩  你在找什么
Shaun, what are you looking for?
肿块  囊肿
Masses? Cysts?
肝脏没问题
They're clean.
你觉得我们遗漏了肿瘤
You think we'd miss a tumor?
没有问题
There's nothing there.
我知道
I know.
没有问题
There's nothing there.
好了  得把肝脏放回冷藏箱
Okay, the liver needs to go back into cold storage,
我们该走了
and we got to go.
然后我松开血管钳
...then I'll release the vascular clamp
让你的血液灌注到移植肝脏里
and let your blood perfuse in your donor liver.
-就行了吗  -连上胆管
- That's it? - Connect the bile ducts,
缝合  然后等待
sew you up, and then we wait.
新器官一般能适应吗
Does the new one always take?
70%以上能
Over 70% of the time.
这个概率我还能接受
Oh, I can live with those odds.
你先休息
You get some rest.
回头见
See you later.
他盯着看  我不知道他在看什么
He looks at something. I don't know what he's looking at.
他是...好奇吗
Is he, you know, is -- is he curious?
他在担心吗  他从不回答我
Is he concerned? He won't answer me.
你跟他交流有困难
You're having trouble communicating with him.
工作日嘛  肖津嘛
It's a weekday. It's Shaun.
再看看吧  听上去问题不大
Hm, let's see. That seems about right.
他似乎跟在医院时不一样
He seemed different at the hospital.
我在医院还能跟他说上话
I could kind of talk to him.
他对医院里的事有心理准备
Well, he knows what to expect in the hospital.
外面就完全不同了  一切都是新事物
Outside, everything's different. Everything's new.
新刺激
New stimuli.
那我该怎么办  我...
So, what do I do? I-I...
我不知道他在想什么
I don't know what he's thinking.
克莱尔  你不会知道他在想什么
Claire, you're not gonna figure out what he's thinking,
所以放弃吧
so don't even try.
其实  如果他在自顾自想什么
In fact, if he's thinking about something in his own mind,
就随他去好了
just let him be.
如果有人这样对我  我会很感激的
I'd appreciate it if people gave me the same courtesy.
我觉得鉴于您的经历...
I thought with your history --
克莱尔  如果你想跟他交流
Claire, if you want to connect with him,
就得找到自己的方法
you're gonna have to figure out your own way in.
查克怎么样了
How's Chuck?
查克  他很好
Chuck? Chuck's fine.
在等肝源
He's waiting for a liver.
所以请赶快回来吧
So come home, please.
好的
Okay.
医生
Doctor.
-什么事  -我想跟你说声谢谢
- What's up? - I just wanted to thank you.
我还什么都没做呢
I haven't done anything yet.
你做了
You have.
你给了我爸爸希望
You've given my dad hope.
查克是我的第一个病人
You know, Chuck was my first patient.
六个月前我在来圣何塞圣文德医院的第一天
Six months ago, - first day at St. Bonaventure,
接受的肝衰患者
I get a liver failure.
他是这个世界上最好的人
And the nicest guy in the world.
我想由我来告诉他这个好消息
I wanted to be the one to give him the good news.
我们走不了了
We're not leaving.
你说过你喜欢直升飞机的
You said you liked helicopters.
我们走不了了
We are not leaving.
我们...我们来的时候很安全
We -- We made it here safe.
是的  但我们走不了了
Yes, we are not leaving.
我们走不了了
We're not leaving.
雾来的太快
Fog's rolling in too quick.
所以去得也快吗
Does that mean it rolls out quick?
可能一小时  也可能三小时
Could be an hour. Could be three.
谁知道
Don't know.
好吧  我们得用别的方法回去了
Okay, uh... We're gonna need a new ride.
打扰一下
Excuse me!
我需要一辆救护车到圣何塞圣文德医院
I need an ambulance to St. Bonaventure.
抱歉  现在没有车搞送货
Sorry. I just don't have the EMS.
80号州际公路发生连环车祸
I've got a pile-up on I-80
四辆车在外待命
and four other vehicles out on call.
一辆救护车都没有吗
Not one ambulance?
听我说  这事很紧急
Let me be clear -- this is emergent.
一分一秒都耽搁不起
It's time sensitive.
亲爱的  这里不是租车行
Honey, this ain't Hertz.
那警车护送呢
What about a police escort?
那倒可以安排
That can be arranged.
当然
Of course.
我不想破坏现在的氛围
Don't want to ruin the festivities.
但是我想和我的病人单独待一会
But if I could just get a few minutes with my patient, alone.
万纳梅克先生
Mr. Wannamaker.
安德鲁斯医生
Dr. Andrews.
今天怎么样
How we doing today?
依旧还有个洞
Incomplete.
那让我们看看有什么办法吧
Let's see what we can do about that.
看这里
Look here.
鉴于肿瘤刚刚切除了不到两周的时间
Well, looking not too bad considering we cut out a tumor
看起来还不错
less than two weeks ago.
是啊  我一直带着嘴边的大洞到处逛
Yeah, I've been walking around with a hole in my mouth.
嘴边带洞喝威士忌试过没有
Ever drink Scotch with a hole in your mouth?
着实浪费了好酒
Waste of good Scotch.
伤口需要一定时间来愈合
We needed to give it time to heal.
知道  知道  你说过了
Yeah, yeah. You told me.
你还抽烟吗
Have you continued to smoke?
抽烟会收缩血管  减缓愈合
It constricts the vessels, slows the healing.
我不是个半途而废的人
I'm not a quitter.
我们准备从你的腿上移植些皮肤
We are going to graft some skin from your leg
将你的脸颊修复得比原来还好
and fix that cheek up better than new.
我是搞房地产的
I'm a real estate guy.
有句老话说
There's an old saying -- "You can have it fast.
「快速  出色和便宜  你得占两条」
You can have it good. You can have it cheap. Pick two."
便宜是占不了
It's not gonna be cheap.
我喜欢你这样的医生
I like doctors like you.
你很出色  你自己知道
You're good, and you know it.
是的  在我们来之前就已经摘取了
Yes. It was harvested before we got there.
我们正等车送我们回去
We're waiting for transportation.
行程和存活时间都有所改变
The itinerary and the life clock have changed.
是的...还剩4小时14分钟
Yeah, uh... Four hours and 14 minutes.
打扰一下  你是在和医院通话吗
Excuse me! Are you talking to the hospital?
麻烦找人转告一下格拉斯曼医生
Have someone tell - Dr. Glassman
我去跟他吃午餐可能会迟到
that I might be late for our lunch, please.
是
Yeah.
好的
Okay.
所以你是怎么预知天气的
So, how did you know about the weather?
是某种天赋吗
Is it some kind of gift?
拜托  我想知道
Come on, I got to know.
难道肖恩・莫菲是宙斯吗
What, Shaun Murphy is Zeus?
我看了天气预报
I watch The Weather Channel.
我要接的医生是你们吗
You my doctors?
肖恩
Shaun?
肖恩  我们得走了
Shaun, we got to go!
你到家了
You're home.
因为你弟弟的事  你爸妈今晚都不太好受
Your dad and mom have had a tough night with your brother and all.
快  走吧
Come on. Let's go.
不要  不要
No! No!
他...他答应过我的
He -- He promised me!
He...He promised me!
他答应了的  他答应过我的
He promised! He promised me!
他答应我的  他答应我的
He promised me! He promised me!
我觉得现在走的话能早点到  肖恩
I think we'll get there much quicker if we drive, Shaun.
能麻烦你把警灯关了吗
C-Could you turn off the flashers, please?
患者的姓名是什么
What's the patient's name?
我告诉过你了  是查克
I told you. It's Chuck.
-不是  -不是
- No. - No?
不是  器官捐献者的名字
No. The -- The donor?
他的名字是什么
What's his name?
什么  肝脏吗
What? The liver?
我...
I...
「奥利弗」
"Oliver"?
奥利弗
Oliver.
你有空吗
Hey, you got a second?
怎么了
What's up?
在等一个肝源
Just waiting on a liver.
移植手术人人都想参与
Transplant. Everyone wants in.
大家宁愿用自己的肝换取参与手术的机会
They'd trade their liver to do the liver.
话说  你的皮瓣移植需要帮忙吗
Hey, look, uh, you want some help on this Free-Flap?
他叫什么来着
What's his name?
万纳梅克
Wannamaker.
你有移植手术要做
You got the transplant.
任何一个主治医生都该忙得不可开交才对
That should keep any attending busy.
我可以挤时间
Well, I can make time.
青木来找过你了
Aoki come to you about this?
听着  我知道  你是主任
Look, I get it. You're the Chief.
没错
That's right.
听着  这不是政治阴谋
Look, this -- this isn't a coup.
那是什么
What is it?
是为了确保我们医院
It's about making sure this hospital is first
成为万纳梅克捐款的首选
on Wannamaker's donation list.
利害关系我清楚得很
I'm aware of the stakes.
多谢你过来告诉我
Thanks for coming by.
你知道的  让我做你的助手
You know, it doesn't make you any less of a surgeon,
对你没有任何坏处
having me in there as your second.
我是你的主任  你是我的主治医师
I'm the Chief. You're my attending.
这没错
Can't argue with that.
你我都清楚你出现在我的手术室里意味着什么
And we both know what your presence in my O.R. will say.
那并不是我的本意
That's not my intention.
重要的是产生的影响  意图不重要
It's the impact. Intention doesn't matter.
谢了  但是我不需要
Thanks...but I'm good.
这肯定有问题
These can't be right.
不管这是哪份报告  没有问题
Whatever it is, it's right.
查克的化验结果
Chuck's labs.
不是弄错了人就是化验结果有误
It's got to be a false flag or a bad reading.
怎么会
For what?
药物  或是食物  我不知道
Medications? Foods? I don't know.
如果结果没错  我们就没法移植了
Look, if this is right, we lose our transplant.
我很抱歉  但结果就是这样
I'm sorry. That doesn't change the results.
他体内有酒精
There's alcohol in his system.
他喝酒了
He drank.
血液不会撒谎
The blood doesn't lie.
重做一遍化验
Run the lab again.
到圣何塞圣文德医院要多久
E.T.A. To St. Bonaventure?
七十分钟
70 minutes.
你在找什么
What are you looking for?
你看到什么了
What do you see?
我有个女邻居
I have a girl neighbor.
哦
Okay.
她人好吗
Is she nice?
她做什么工作的  有男朋友吗
What does she do? - Does she...have a boyfriend?
你知道她叫什么吗
Do you know her name?
你到底在片子上找什么呢
What the hell are you looking for on the scans?
怎么会
What the...
温度在升高
The temperature is going up!
警官  我们得找个有冰的地方  马上
Officer, we need to find a place with ice, like, now!
我验过了  查克  验了两遍
I tested it, Chuck. And re-tested it.
说话啊  你知道六个月内不能喝酒的规定
Talk to me. You know the six-month rule.
-是忍不住吗  -是三天前
- Was it a craving? - It was three days ago.
我女儿的毕业典礼
My daughter's graduation.
我们家里没有人上过大学
Nobody in my family had ever gone to college.
她就站在那
There she was.
我的宝贝女儿穿着学士服
My little girl wearing the robes.
那一天我只想做个平凡的父亲
And for just that day, I...I wanted to be normal.
所以我喝了一杯香槟
So, I...I had a glass of champagne.
你们没有冰了
You're out of ice?
冰箱坏了  五公里外有个超市
It's broken. Supermarket's about three miles down.
我们没时间了
We don't have time.
好吧  好吧
Okay. Okay.
温度已经到八摄氏度了
The temperature's already at 47 degrees.
我们不能让它再继续升高了
We can't let it go any higher.
你不来帮我吗
Are you gonna help me?
甜的  你会喜欢的
It's sweet. You'll like it.
我该拿他怎么办
What should I do with him?
儿童保护机构在夏延
Child Services is down in Cheyenne.
有240公里远  而且他们肯定会
That's 150 miles, and they'll just turn me around
打发我调头送到他父母那里
and send me back to the parents.
他父母不想要他吗
The parents don't want him?
不知道
I don't know.
可以肯定的是他不想要他父母
He doesn't seem to want the parents, that's for sure.
你可以带他去医院
You can take him to do the hospital.
那有社工
Social worker there.
这样不管用
That won't work.
你怎么知道
How do you know?
肖恩
Shaun?
你说得对  不管用  为什么
You're right. It's not working! Why?
肖恩
Shaun!
你到底有没有在听我说话
Are you even listening to me?!
只喝了一杯
Just one drink?
他是这么说的
That's what he said.
要不要通知器官移植登记中心
Should I inform the registry?
查克多长时间以前喝的那杯酒
How long ago - did Chuck have that drink?
三天前
Three days ago.
把记号笔给我
Give me your marker.
这是
That's...
血液酒精含量估计值
Estimated blood-alcohol content.
他喝的是什么酒
What type of alcohol?
香槟
Uh, champagne.
酒精含量是多少
What percentage of alcohol is that?
我不知道  有什么关系吗
I don't know. What's the difference?
把手机拿出来查查
Take out your phone and look it up.
我不知道为什么它不管用
I don't know why it's not working!
要被冰水淹没才可以
It needs to be submerged to cool.
每开五秒就是一份特大杯沙冰
Every five seconds is an XL.
为什么最后一次你回答我了  之前不回答
Why did you answer me the last time, but not before?
是因为我生气了吗
Was it because I was angry?
是巧合吗
Was it random?
为什么你就不能回答我的问题
Why can't you answer my questions?
最好管用
This better work.
会管用的
It will work.
我不问你就会说
You answer when I don't ask.
你不喜欢问题
You don't like questions.
不喜欢
I don't.
我微积分没学好
I didn't do well in calculus.
这是代数
This is algebra.
他有重度肝硬化
With his severe cirrhosis,
酒精清除率为每小时一毫克每分升
his alcohol-clearance rate is one milligram per deciliter per hour.
一杯酒  就算八盎司
One drink, say eight ounces...
香槟的话最多六盎司
If it's champagne, six ounces, tops.
按保守估计
Play it conservative.
八盎司导致血液酒精浓度
Eight ounces results in a blood alcohol level
上升39毫克每分升
of 39 milligrams per deciliter.
这是标准杯量
One standard drink.
而禁酒的目的
Now, the purpose of abstinence,
至少根据移植中心的说法...
at least according to the transplant registry is...
是让由过量饮酒引起肝病的患者
Patients who kill their livers due to excessive drinking
证明自己可以戒酒
prove they can be sober.
给我看一下报告
Let me see that report.
0.02
查克说的是实话
Chuck was telling the truth.
他确实只喝了一杯
He did have just the one drink.
他没有中断戒酒
He didn't fall off the wagon.
董事会会喜欢这个数据
Corporate loves its data.
我不确定这是否有用
I'm not sure it'll actually make a difference,
但至少给了我们论据
but it does give us an argument.
你是个天才
You are a genius.
你不喜欢食堂的饭菜吗
You don't like the cafeteria food?
他们能把东西做熟就不错了
They only make one thing well.
要是员工看见他们的院长
What does it say when the staff sees
不吃食堂的饭菜会怎么想
the President of the hospital not eating their cafeteria food?
这说明院长
Well, it says the President of the hospital
不允许进厨房
isn't allowed in the kitchen.
你坐这的意思是我能为你做什么吗
You sat down. What can I do for you?
我想听听你的建议
I'd like your advice.
是吗
Really?
青木呢  她去世了吗
Where's Aoki? Did she die?
这真是个错误
This was a mistake.
这么说真伤人啊  坐下吧
That's insulting. Sit down.
至少听完我要说什么
At least hear what I have to say,
再说这是个坏主意
and then decide it's bad advice.
坐吧
Sit.
青木把梅伦德斯推给我参与VIP的手术
Aoki is pushing Melendez on me for the VIP.
你没看到群发邮件吧
You didn't get the e-mail blast.
有钱人不能死在这家医院里
Rich people aren't allowed to die in this hospital.
你不再是明日之星了
You're not the young star anymore.
梅伦德斯才是
Melendez is.
我知道
I know that.
那你还为「为什么」而苦恼吗
And you're upset about the "Why"?
为什么青木这么想
Why does Aoki think that?
你应该问的是「谁」
You should be asking "Who".
「谁」  我知道是谁  梅伦德斯
"Who"? I know who. Melendez.
你是「谁」
Who are you?
你是想当顶级外科医生的主任
Are you a Chief who wants to be top surgeon,
还是个想当院长的主任
or are you a Chief who wants to be president?
因为若是后者  就收起你的自我
'Cause if it's the latter, take your ego,
塞进什么碗柜里
shove it in a cupboard somewhere,
表现得像个院长的样子
and start acting presidential.
梅伦德斯医生会和董事会沟通
Dr. Melendez is going to argue to the board
让你移植这个肝脏
that you get this liver.
我认为胜算很大
And I think it's a pretty good argument.
我值得吗
Do I deserve it?
我认为这与此无关
I'm... not sure that's relevant.
你知道吗
You know...
当人濒死时
when you're dying,
而我已经濒死很久了
and I've been dying for a long time,
你会开始思考自己的人生
you start to think about your life.
我的人生不尽人意
I haven't led a great one.
我本该成为一个更好的父亲
I could've been a better dad.
更好的男人
A better man.
告诉你  我曾酗酒
News flash, I drank too much.
我还有个儿子
You know, I also have a son.
第一次婚姻时生的
Yeah. First marriage.
我有三年没见过他了
I haven't seen him in three years.
肝脏移植不是你的第二次生命
Getting a liver is not a second chance,
也不是给好人的奖励
and it's not a reward for being perfect.
只是我们能做的
It's just what we can do.
也许吧
Maybe.
但在移植登记中心里
But on the registry,
我们所有人都排着队
all of us wait in line together.
而我看到...
And I see these ...
那些人等着
these people here, waiting.
我认识他们的脸
I know their faces.
甚至知道他们的名字
Even their names.
他们都有各自的故事
They all have stories.
我们一起排在上面
We're in it together.
而我...
And I...
我打破了...
I broke the...
查克  查克
Chuck? Chuck!
查克  紧急呼叫
Chuck? Code blue!
查克  你能听见吗
Chuck, can you hear me?
他食管里有血
He's got blood in his esophagus.
静脉曲张出血
He's got a variceal bleed.
开一袋生理盐水  交叉配型四个单位
All right. Saline wide open. Type and cross four units.
我来结扎静脉
I'm going to band the vein.
血压回升了
Pressure's coming up.
-查克静脉曲张出血  -我也在场
- Chuck had a variceal bleed. - I was in there.
门脉高压  代偿失调
Portal hypertension, decompensated...
你说完了吗
Are you finished?
他可能只剩三个月了
He's got three months to live, maybe.
他得禁酒六个月
You have to be six-months alcohol free
才有资格进入移植名单
before you're registry eligible.
你还说自己数学不好呢
And you said you weren't good at math.
他得不到这个肝源就必死无疑
He gets this one or he dies.
你知道早上八点坐警车是什么体验吗
You know what this thing looks like at 8:00 A.M.?
我需要警车每天早上护送我上班
I need a police escort to work every morning.
所有道路都在
280 South.
280号公路南段汇聚
Where are all roads meet.
不对
No, they don't!
-他怎么了  -他有自闭症  警官
- What's wrong with him? - He's autistic, officer.
那是什么意思
What's that mean?
他需要去医院吗
Does he need to be in a hospital?
他最不该去的地方就是医院
The last place he should be is a hospital.
你在做什么
What are you doing?
肖恩
Shaun?
你在想什么
What are you thinking?
好吧  我不是在问你问题
Okay, this isn't a question.
我只是  我不知道你在找什么  肖恩
I just...I don't know what you're looking for, Shaun.
我感觉得到  它变得更紧实了
Yes, I can feel it. It's firmer.
然后呢
And?
我不知道那是什么意思
I don't know what that means.
这里面肯定有凝块  但我找不到
There must be a clot, but there isn't a clot.
片子里看不到凝块
The scan showed no clot.
那是因为片子是在
That's because the scans were taken before
摘除肝脏之前拍的
they harvested the liver.
那时肝脏还没有用UW液冲洗
Prior to the liver being flushed with UW solution!
它要死了
It's dying!
为了保存肝脏  他们把里面的血液
To preserve the liver, they replace all its blood
全部替换为防止肝脏被冻伤的溶液
with a solution to protect it from the cold storage,
但里面肯定残留了血液  形成了凝块
but they must've left some blood behind, which clotted.
离圣文德医院还有多远
How long to St. Bonaventure?
-不到三十分钟  -来不及了
- Less than 30 minutes. - Can't wait!
我们必须马上清除凝块  冲洗左叶
We have to immediately remove the clot and flush the left lobe
防止肝脏冻伤
to protect it from the ice bath.
必须马上停车
We need to stop the car.
-在这里吗  -对  对
- Here? - Yes. Yes.
我们必须马上就地操作
We need to operate right here, right now.
从右边进行冲洗
Flush this from the right.
左叶
So, the left lobe,
从肝中静脉开始
starting at the middle hepatic vein.
沿镰状韧带做切口进入第三肝段
Less intrusive cut would be along the falciform ligament
侵入性更低
to allow access to Segment III.
你定位堵塞点  我来清除
When you locate the blockage, I'm gonna have to remove it.
我需要一根吸管做静脉插管
I need a straw to cannulate the vein, please.
我杯子里有根吸管
There's a straw in my cup.
UW溶液可以稳定细胞壁
UW solution will stabilize the cell walls.
保护器官的完整性
Preserve the integrity of the organ.
这总比在我车里生孩子强
This is better than having a baby in my car.
你感觉怎么样
How are you feeling?
像在开空头支票
Like I'm writing a blank check.
你会没事的
You're gonna be fine.
你是最好的医生
You're the best.
出血  静脉曲张  这些都不是好现象
This bleed, these varices -- this isn't good news.
说明你的肝衰竭严重恶化了
Tells us that your liver failure has progressed considerably.
有多严重
How much?
你还能活两到三个月
You have two to three months.
我们今天就有肝源了  一个小时后
We're getting - the liver today, in an hour.
我不明白你在说什么
I don't get it.
你没告诉她们
You didn't tell them.
什么
What?
你父亲喝酒了
Your father had a drink.
他就喝了一杯
He had one glass.
移植登记中心不管你喝了多少
Transplant registry doesn't quantify things like that.
所以他得不到这个肝源了吗
So he doesn't get the liver?
我会试着帮他争取
I'm gonna try and get it for him.
你是汽车销售员吗
What are you, a car salesman?
只会试试
What, you're gonna try?
最终决定权不在我这
The final decision is out of my hands.
如果你失败了呢
And if you fail?
我会竭尽全力
I'm gonna do everything that I can.
我十分钟后跟委员会开会
I am meeting with - the committee in 10 minutes.
失陪了
Excuse me.
那杯酒是我递给我爸爸的
I handed my dad the drink.
事情经过不重要
Doesn't matter how it happened.
他不想喝的  只是想让我开心
He didn't want it. He just wanted to make me happy.
如果你不救他  就是我亲手杀死了他
If you let him die, I will have killed my father.
就一杯
It was a glass.
他女儿的毕业典礼上的一杯香槟
A glass of champagne at his daughter's graduation.
化验结果可以证明
I have the labs to prove it.
查克没有中断戒酒
Chuck didn't fall off the wagon.
他只喝了一杯  仅此而已
He had one drink and never went back.
移植登记中心的指南
The transplant registry guidelines don't play
不留余地是有原因的
in the gray for a reason.
那些规定太专制了
Those guidelines are so arbitrary.
喝一杯酒就被剥夺生的希望
Have one drink and you die.
吃摇头丸却没问题
A couple pills of ecstasy, no problem.
高危性行为导致的乙型肝炎也没问题
Hepatitis B from careless sexual practice, nope.
什么规定都没有
Nothing at all about that.
所以你想我们怎么做  无视规定吗
So, what do you want us to do? Throw out the rules?
我希望我们不要拿规定当挡箭牌
I want us not to hide behind them.
负起责任来
We do have a responsibility.
没有了规则  那我们就是在扮演上帝
Without the rules, we're playing God.
我们需要规则
We need the rules.
它会让你晚上睡得更安稳吗
Does that help you sleep better at night?
会
Yes, it does.
全州有八百人需要今天这个肝源
We have one liver today, and 800 people in this state need it.
我不想对另外799人心怀愧疚
I don't want to be haunted by the other 799.
你的病人自己丢掉了这个机会
Your guy hasn't earned it.
他知道规定  这...
He knew the rules, and this...
这是一个技术性细则
it's a technicality.
不  这杯酒才是一个技术性细则
No, the drink is a technicality.
杰西卡  这里面涉及什么法律责任
Jessica, what's the legal burden here?
十分重大
Significant.
如果我们进行移植
If we move forward with this transplant,
可能会失去移植中心的特权
we could lose privileges from the registry.
-如果被发现的话  -如果被发现
-If it were discovered. -If it were discovered?
你是有多狭隘
How narrow can you be about this?
格拉斯曼医生  你怎么看
Dr. Glassman, where are you on this?
两边都有理
I can make a good argument either way.
请继续
Go ahead, please.
最好将这些争论都解决掉
Better to remove - the arguments all together.
他到底在说什么
What the hell is he talking about?
我是说我们医院有个患者
All I'm talking about is that we have a patient
需要肝源
in this hospital who needs a liver.
我们也恰好有一个肝脏需要一个患者
We also just happen to have a liver that needs a patient.
没那么简单
It's not that simple.
如果你为患者考虑就这么简单
It is that simple if you consider the patient.
规则是次要的
Rules are secondary.
但救这个患者值得我们承担
But is saving this patient worth the risk
救不了剩下几百个的风险吗
of not being able - to save hundreds of others?
我现在没有几百个患者
I don't have hundreds of patients right now.
只有一个  他叫查克
I have one, and his name is Chuck.
血压稳定
Blood pressure's steady.
面动脉接入供体血管
Donor vessel to the facial artery,
准备缝合
and we're ready to close him up.
10-0缝合线和血管钳
10-0 polypropylene and vascular forceps.
干得好  安德鲁斯医生
Nice work, Dr. Andrews.
这是什么
What do we have here?
血肿
hematoma?
我看见了  找出来源吧
I can see that. Let's find its source.
纱布棒  探针
Sponge, stick, and probe.
不是受体动脉
It's not my recipient artery.
心率在下降
Heart rate is dropping.
不管是什么  都在压迫他的颈动脉
Whatever it is, - it's compressing his carotid.
我无法深入病灶  需要更好的切口
I can't get deep enough here. I need better access.
从外部进入第三区
We move through zone three from the outside.
第三区是危险区
Zone three's a minefield.
我知道  但必须这样做
I'm aware, but we need to do this.
不管你做什么  赶紧
Whatever you're gonna do, do it quick.
里面的东西正威胁着他
It's strangling him from the inside.
叫梅伦德斯过来
Get me Melendez.
赶到了
We made it!
是啊  我们到了
Yeah, we're here.
下楼  来吧
Downstairs, coming up.
不不不  杰瑞德  你肯定不信
No, no, no. Jared, you're not gonna believe wh--
啊
Yeah?
知道了
Got it.
查克被放在了名单最后
Chuck's been moved to the bottom of the list.
圣何塞长老会医院正过来取肝源
San Jose Presbyterian are coming to get the liver.
-血氧饱和度下降  -给予100%浓度吸氧
-Oxygen sats tanking. -Up him to 100 % O2.
你得从里面穿过下颌
You have to go through the mandible from the inside
来探测来源  只能这样
to probe for the source. It's the only way.
手术放大镜
Loupes.
我们必须小心  否则他可能会中风
We have to be careful in there, or he'll get a stroke.
我们需要的只是小心
We'll just have to be careful then.
给梅伦德斯医生下颌槽状拉钩
Give Dr. Melendez - the mandibular channel retractor
和五号骨刀
and number five bone cutter.
五号骨刀
number five bone cutter.
存活时间剩余29分钟
29 minutes. That's a lifetime.
谢谢  真是太好了
Thank you. This is amazing.
我得走了  整个组都等着呢
Got to go. The whole team is waiting.
他叫奥利弗
His name is Oliver.
真是美好的一天
It was a good day.
我们拯救了一个生命
We saved a life...
只不过不是查克的
just not Chuck's.
这不是你的错
It's not your fault.
我也想相信
I want to believe that.
你好
Hello.
你是个实验员还是
Are you a lab guy or something?
-我是个外科医生  -那太疯狂了
- I'm a surgeon. - That's insane.
我能要回我的电池吗
May I have my batteries back?
你借的那些
The ones you borrowed.
好啊
Yeah.
给你
There you go.
你叫什么名字
What's your name?
我叫莉亚
I'm Lea.
我是肖恩・莫菲医生  很高兴认识你
I'm Dr. Shaun Murphy. Nice to meet you.
你今晚就跟我待在一起
You'll stay with me tonight.
明天我们再解决其他事
And tomorrow, - we'll figure out the rest.